<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The resurrection of John Lilburne, now a prisoner in Dover-Castle, declared and manifested in these following lines penned by himself, and now at his desire published in print in these following words.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E880_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206594</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117964</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88248)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117964)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E880[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The resurrection of John Lilburne, now a prisoner in Dover-Castle, declared and manifested in these following lines penned by himself, and now at his desire published in print in these following words.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, with remarkable additions by way of appendex.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the Black Spread Eagle, neer the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. May. 21.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117964:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117964:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RESURRECTION OF JOHN LILBURNE, NOW A PRISONER IN Dover-Caſtle, DECLARED And manifeſted in theſe following Lines, penned by himſelf, and now at his earneſt deſire publiſhed in print in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Edition, with remarkable Additions by way of Appendex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black Spread Eagle,</hi> neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117964:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117964:2"/>
            <head>THE RESURRECTION OF <hi>John Lilburne, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving many and ſtrong compulſions, from the meaſure of the light of the Lord now ſhining clearly within me, and raiſed up now to a good degree of life and power in my ſoul, to <hi>make a publike declaration in print,</hi> of my reall owning, and now living in, (in my preſent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to meaſure) the <hi>life and power of thoſe divine and heavenly principles, profeſſed by thoſe spirituallized people called</hi> Quakers; at my ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of which, all my old and familliar friends (in a manner) are ſo much troubled and offended with me for, and my great adverſaries ſo jealous of the reall intentions of my heart within me, at my ſo doing, and by that meaſure of the Light of JESUS ſhining in my ſoul, I am now directed and guided to intitle it as aforeſaid, and here at this place (as an introduction, before I come to the main thing of that which through the ſtrength of God I have now to ſay) to inſert here the copies of the very two firſt Letters, that ever I writ of note, after the great and glorious power of God had ſeized upon my ſoul, to let in the real begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nings of convincement into my ſoul, of my ſpiritual blindneſs, deadneſs and emptineſs, and by which I came to ſee a clear glimps of that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual fulneſs that was, and really is, in the divine and heavenly declared principles of the aforeſaid precious people: The firſt Letter being to my wife, take in theſe following words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dover-Caſtle</hi> 
                        <date> the fourth day of the tenth moneth, 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>For my deer and loving wife <hi>Elizabeth Lilburn,</hi> at her friend <hi>George Wades (houſe)</hi> a Cook, at the Sign of the <hi>Sun</hi> neer <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> and <hi>Lawrence Lanes end</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> theſe with ſpeed deliver.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My dear heart,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHat in a great meaſure my temper of ſpirit was before thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, I in its meaſure communicated unto thee, by the copy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117964:3"/>of my letter to <hi>Luke Howard,</hi> which I have here incloſed thee at thy lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to peruſe: And what diſtemperedneſs my earthly ſpirit was in, at, and towards thee, at thy and my laſt meeting upon <hi>Saturday,</hi> the tenth of <hi>November</hi> laſt, I need not to repeat unto thee, being (I beleeve) it is freſh enough in thy own memory.</p>
                  <p>And the frame of my heart, after thy reconciliation and mine (ſo far as God hath given me the ſpirit of diſcerning, and ſearching it) I in no ſmall proportion in reallity diſcovered to thee.</p>
                  <p>And ſince my departue (upon <hi>VVedneſday</hi> the 21. of <hi>November</hi> laſt) ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting my-ſelf ſeriouſly to a deep and weighty conſideration of that work that my ſoul longed for a new to be a travelling in; <hi>And giving fulneſs of ſcope to that divine and heavenly voice of God ſpeaking plainly in my heart,</hi> unto which I am truly able to ſet my ſeal to, that it is that ſpirit, or power of the Holy Ghoſt, or true Comforter, ſpoken of Joh. 16.7, 8. <hi>that convinceth, or reproveth the world, or the carnal, or firſt, or fallen nature in me, of ſin, and of righteouſneſs, and of judgement,</hi> and is that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and everlaſting ſpirit of truth, that (imbraced and cloſed with) leads my ſoul by its divine and ſtrong power, or attractive drawings, ſtep by ſtep in its meaſure and degree into truth, and in my heavenly fathers good time, <hi>I doubt not but it will eſtabliſh and build me up in truth, Ioh.</hi> 16.13. and mould me into a real conformity in life and power (in real and ſubſtantial injoyment) <hi>to the wayes of truth, of light, and life, be they never ſo difficult to the fleſh,</hi> carnal man, or fallen, or firſt nature in me, or never ſo full of the croſs, or ſelf-denyall, or giving up my own reaſon, underſtanding, will, wiſdom, and affections, to be croſſed and crucified by the Will and Wiſdom of JESUS, <hi>the annoynted above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Father, and to be guided or led on by him the living life, light, or power in all the ſons of men,</hi> that have the greateſt degree, or leaſt of ſparks of divine or heavenly light, ſhining within their dark, (in their ſmall degree or meaſure) or inlightned, inlivened ſouls, in their lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger degree or meaſure.</p>
                  <p>I have, ſince I ſee thee, read extraordinary much of thoſe two volumes which I ſhewed thee, containing both almoſt ſeventeen hundred pages, of the writings of thoſe preciouſeft (though moſt contemptible) people called <hi>quakers; the truly beloved objects of my ſoul.</hi> And this at preſent, (becauſe I rather now heartily deſire to live in the poſſeſſion, power, or life of truth in my ſoul, then in the bare profeſſion, notion, or talk of it) I ſhall, and can in ſincerity ſay to thee, <hi>that my ſoul hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, and even confounded by them;</hi> not as <hi>Herod</hi> by <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings was, for fear of eternal wrath (or loſs of his Tetrarch-ſhip by, or) for his ſins, which to avoid made him reform, and amend many things, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.20. but of real breakings, or ſhame of ſoul, that ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Talent, as my Lord and Maſter (by the clear, lively, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full breakings in of his divine and heavenly light into my heart) long, and many yeers ago beſtowed upon me, ſhould by me <hi>(or my firſt, and carnal wiſdom)</hi> be moſt ungratefully, and unfaithfully, like a lighted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117964:3"/>candle put under a buſhel, or hid, or buried in the earth in me, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and darkneſs: Or, that my ſoul ſhould by the will and wiſdom of the firſt nature, ambitiouſly (<hi>Adam</hi>-like) eat anew upon the tree of Knowledge of good and evill, and thereby covet to be eſteemed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing amongſt the ſons of men, (more then the Divine Wiſdom would have me) with that meaſure or degree I had attained to; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with be with it (like the unbelieving Jews, the type in the fleſh) or the firſt (or mean in its degree or meaſure, to what I ought to have thirſted after) out-goings of the divine and heavenly teaching, and inſtructing ſpirit, or voice of God in, or unto my ſoul, willing and content to ſit down in the wilderneſs, or journeying way to <hi>Canaan;</hi> and not with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> (the ſpiritual anti-types in that particular, or in another particular, the outward types, of the ſpiritual travelling anti-types, <hi>the ſeed of God under the Goſpel, into Gods ſpiritual reſt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi>) be willing, longing, and deſirous, by faith in the ſtrength of God, (reſting as the old Iſraelites after the fleſh ought to have done, in his faithfull and powerfull promiſe of carrying me on) through all <hi>difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſelf-denyals, croſſes, and hardſhips whatſoever;</hi> to travell into the <hi>ſpiritual Kingdom,</hi> or <hi>heavenly Land of Reſt, that God in the naked injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of himſelf hath prepared for</hi> (and at this very day I beleeve hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally and really beſtowed the clear injoyment of, upon many of) <hi>his Ranſomed ones, contemptibly and ſcornfully called</hi> quakers.</p>
                  <p>I ſay unto thee, the real (and cloſe applyed home unto my ſoul by the ſpirit and power of life from God, <hi>that now aloud again ſpeaks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me</hi>) conſideration of the premiſes, or that which is foregoing, and that people afar off, (<hi>yea, ignorant ideots, fools and prophane</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">As is clearly proved by the printed ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of ſeverall of the priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton and Everſham Goals.</note> 
                     <hi>ones</hi>) in compariſon of my being ſo nigh at hand ſo many yeers ago, to the clear and full poſſeſſion of the ſpiritual Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſhould enter into the glorious Kingdom of God, or that clearneſs of Reſt, Peace and Union in, and with him, that now clearly to my ſpiritual underſtanding they iajoy, and there bring forth the ripe fruits of ſpiritual old age in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of me, of Praiſes, Honor, and Glory to the Lamb: <hi>and to the ancient of Dayes, that clearly ſits upon the Throne in their hearts,</hi> as having judged down, conquered, and overcome, within them, all their ſinns or ſpiritual enemies, and cauſed them to triumph over them, as in his ſtrength, divine and heavenly power, reigning and ruling as King and Lord over them.</p>
                  <p>O, I ſay unto thee again, the real ſight (in its meaſure and degree) and ſpiritual conſideration of theſe things, ſince I laſt ſee thee, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers hours in ſeveral nights, one after another, <hi>when my God denyed ſleep unto my outward eyes, and cauſed my ſoul to be awake with himſelfe,</hi> and to be really exerciſed in an interchange of Divine conference, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation or parley with him, <hi>hath even cauſed my ſoul to weep, ſigh, and mourn within me before him,</hi> and in his ſtrength and almighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to indent with him, and now in good earneſt to ingage in my ſoul, or ſpiritual man, to be obedient to his heavenly and divine voyce, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117964:4"/>clearly in me, and to follow him (leaſt I ſhould now by any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reſiſtance, totally quench his divine drawings) through the denyal of my own (or natural reaſon) will, wit, wiſdom, deſires and affections, and with a real weanedneſs from worldly or fleſhly honour, applauſe, glory, riches, or creature-fulneſs, yea, even to a final denyal of father, kindred, friends, my ſweet and dearly beloved (by me) babes, or thy own ſelf, who <hi>viz.</hi> thy ſelf, for many yeers by-paſt, I muſt avow it before the Almighty in ſincerity and truth, hath been to me the greateſt &amp; deareſt of all earthly delights and joyes.</p>
                  <p>And now therefore look about thee in good earneſt, and ſee what thou haſt got to thy ſelf, as to the fleſh, by thy eager deſires, and ſtrong indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to bring me back again into England; for the day of thy real, ſtrong, and full temptation and trial, never came upon thee till now, if God give thee not by degrees the fulneſs and compleatneſs of ſpiritual and heavenly ſtrength and ability to bear it, and go through it. For my part I am now in reallity and truth, in the clearly, lively, or evident ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the wiſdom, and loving hand of a tender and indeared eternal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſtripping me naked of all earthly and created excellencies, and taking my outward Eſtate, and profitable worldly Imployment, and all my worldly glory from me, and graciouſly, and ſupportingly leading me through the valley of <hi>Baca, Pſal.</hi> 84.6. or tears, outward dangers, and death, for now almoſt four yeers together, and ſeperating fromme for a long time, that wonted delight that uſed to be betwixt thee (my old and real I doll) and me; and at my coming to this place, clearly unrobeing me of all and every one of my old friends, and familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, that were any way fit, or able to do any thing for me; and thereby hedging up my way, that I muſt, whether I will or no, in ſpite of my teeth, once again give ear to the ſerious and plain voice, call, or counſel of the moſt High, ſpeaking in, and unto my ſoul.</p>
                  <p>And ſo in much mercy and indeared loving kindneſs, as he did in my great ſtraits in the Biſhops time, prouided and ſent to me a poor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed (yet underſtanding) <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> to inſtruct me in, or expound unto me the way of God more fully, or perfectly; (whom I am compell'd now to tell thee, I ſhall love reſpect therefore, the longeſt day I live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, let her continue by whomſoever to be judged never ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid or contemptible) ſo here at his place he hath alſo provided for me an <hi>Aquilla,</hi> (being a contemptible, yet underſtanding, ſpiritually know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp; ſingle hearted Shoomaker) to do the ſame now to my ſpiritual, &amp; no ſmall advantage, refreſhment, &amp; benefit, by means of all which I am at preſent become dead to my former buſling acting in the world, and now ſtand ready with the devour centurion or captain, ſpoken of <hi>Act.</hi> 10. <hi>to hear and obey all things that the lively voice of God speaking in my ſoul ſhal require of me,</hi> upon the further manifeſtation of whoſe glorious preſence, my heart with a watching fear &amp; care deſires to wait, and to walk faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and tenderly, and humbly in that meaſure of Light already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and out of the ſtrength of indearedneſs of love, and tenderneſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117964:4"/>of affection, that hath long in times by-paſt, dwelt in me towards thee <hi>and of late in much ſincerity is renewed unto thee again;</hi> I have with the ſame eternal, wel-wiſhing of thy-ſpiritual happineſs, as I do my own, ordered <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> to ſend unto thee ſeveral of thoſe <hi>printed pieces of the quakers, that in the ſerious reading of which have been moſt convincingly, inſtructive unto my ſoul;</hi> amongſt which I have judged in the firſt place <hi>Iames Naylor</hi> (that ſtrong, or tall man in Chriſt) his <hi>Something in anſwer unto (thy and my indeared friend)</hi> John Jackſon <hi>(that tall Cedar in great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion) his book called,</hi> Strength in weakneſs, <hi>(which book the laſt Poſt I received from thee)</hi> in the reading of which piece of <hi>Iames Naylors,</hi> I muſt ſet my ſeal to it, that there goes along in the breathings out of it a great deal of the quickning life &amp; power of the ſpirit of God, &amp; unto it are annexed ſeveral pieces of that precious and divine ſoul, <hi>VVilliam Deusbury,</hi> the Lords now, or late glorious priſoner, in <hi>Northampton common goal,</hi> (to whoſe precious and heavenly ſpirit, although I never ſee his face, mine in indearedneſs of love is glued unto) whoſe books is cald, <hi>The diſcovery of the great enmity of the Serpent againſt the Seed of the woman, and his diſcovery of mans return,</hi> have been pieces in my reading of them ſeriouſly, that by the power of the <hi>Almighty</hi> hath ſpoken home to my <hi>ſoul</hi> I have ordered to be annexed unto them (as I remember) as many as makes them ten in number; and then twelve more in another volume principally for anſwering <hi>Objections,</hi> I have ordered to be ſent unto thee, which I hope thou wilt receive (before this come to thee) bound up in that method that J have directed.</p>
                  <p>And now my dear love, <hi>for whom my ſoul travells with God for thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good, with the ſame ſincere heartedneſs as for my own,</hi> hoping that thy late out-fall and mine was but for a ſet ſeaſon, that ſo as divine <hi>Paul</hi> in another ſenſe ſpeaks, <hi>Phil.</hi> 15. <hi>thy reconciliation and mine again might now remain firm in love for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I therefore earneſtly intreat thee, not to much cumber thy ſelf in thy many toi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and journeyings for my outward liberty, but ſit down a little, and behold the</hi> great ſalvation <hi>of the</hi> Lord; and if by any means poſſible thy ſpirit can be made free to it, retire thy ſelf but for one week, or the like, into thy own chamber (as being ſequeſtred from all thy friends &amp; acquaintance) and with as much ſeriouſneſs and deliberation read this, and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned precious books, with the letter that thy &amp; my indeared, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, &amp; faithful friend, <hi>Luke Howard,</hi> yeſterday ſent unto thee (as the real out goings of the meaſure of the ſpirit of God in his heart towards thee) as I have often and deliberately read thy laſt Poſt-letter to me, Dated at <hi>VVhits-Hall,</hi> upon Wedneſeday the 28, of November laſt, and often wept for joy and gladneſs of heart, at that they honeſt exhortation to me, at the laſt and of it in thoſe words, viz. <hi>My Dear, Retain a ſober patient ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within thee, which I am confident thou ſhalt ſee ſhall be of more force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover thee, then all thy keen m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>tal hath been; I hope God is a doing a work upon thee and me too, as ſhall make us ſtudy our ſelves more then we have done.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117964:5"/>
                  <p>O my dear Love, I am deeply already entred into my part of it: The mighty power of God inable thee to get in too, and alſo to go through thine, and effectually to go cheerfully &amp; willingly along hand in hand with me, which abundantly would render thee more amiable, lovely, and pleaſant in mine eyes, although thou wert then clothed in rags, then thou couldſt be to me in thy drawings back, or ſtanding ſtill where thou waſt when I laſt ſee thee, though therein thou wert clothed all over with rich, and outwardly gliſtering earthly Diamonds, and in the greateſt of earthly proſperities.</p>
                  <p>I am ſorry for that hard portion thou tell'ſt me thou hadſt in going from me, in thy dangerous travelling upon the Thames, <hi>and I deſire to bleſs</hi> God <hi>for thy deliverance from ſo nigh a death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am alſo ſorry thou art ſo ſtraightly put to it for money, <hi>but to live upon God by faith in the depth of ſtraights, is the lively condition of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: O that thy spirit could attain unto it!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>According to thy deſire in thy Letter, and my own preſent genius or frame of Spirit (<hi>which now can contentedly feed ſavourily upon bread and cheeſe, and Small-Beer</hi> alone) for ſaving of money. I have diſcharged my old Nurſe, and borrowed 20. s. to give her to carry her towards her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and by her have I ſent theſe lines to deliver to thine own hands.</p>
                  <p>Of which, poor ignorant ſoul, I muſt ſay this to thee in truth, that although the woman, in my clear underſtanding, be but wholly in the firſt nature of fallen man-kinde, <hi>yet ſhe hath been in the hand of God, an inſtrument of much ſervice,</hi> (honeſty performed) <hi>faithfulneſs, and tender compaſſion to me, in the day of the greateſt and unparalelled extremity of my outward deſires in the</hi> Iſle of Jerſey, for which, in her ſtation, I muſt value her as long as I live, and if ever outward proſperity in any competent degree be my portion, really requite her; therefore I expect from thee, if ſhe have occaſion to uſe thee, <hi>that thou beeſt tender and respectful to her for my ſake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for my <hi>Liberty,</hi> about which thou ſo wearieſt and ſpendeſt thy ſelf and earthly ſtrength, as thy Letter acquaints me with thou doſt, I can ſay no more to thee then what was contained in my <hi>Letter,</hi> directed to thee, and Dated <hi>Nov.</hi> 21. laſt, (which I gave here to thy own hands) but that I am in my preſent temper of ſpirit, ready really with <hi>Peter</hi> at the ſight of the <hi>glorlous tranſfiguration</hi> of Chriſt, to ſay, <hi>its good being here</hi> (for me) for here in <hi>Dover Caſtle,</hi> through the loving kindneſs of God, I have met with a more clear, plain, and evident knowledge of God and my ſelf, and his gracious out-goings to my ſoul, then ever I had in all my life time, not excepting my glorying and rejoycing condition under the Biſhops, and now the pangs and travelling throes of God are powerfully afreſh upon my very heart, and therefore now in my own will, I could rather wiſh thee and my ſweet Lambs to be with me here, then I at preſent with thee and them where thou art, yet ſubmiſſively and heartily I ſay, and can ſay, the Will of my heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117964:5"/>Father be done in me, by me, and for me; in whoſe Will I leave thee and thine, with all thy and my friends, and reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From Dover-Caſtle, the place of the preſent injoyed delightfull diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of the eternal, everlaſting love of God unto my ſoul, <date>the 4th. day of the 10 th. moneth, 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Thine in the ſtrength of renewedneſs of true love, John Lilburn</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The forementioned ſecond Letter, take in theſe following words.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> 
                        <date>the fifth day of the tenth moneth, 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>
                     <hi>For my indeared friend</hi> William Harding, <hi>commonly called Mayor, at</hi> Weymouth in Dorcetſhire, <hi>theſe deliver.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Kind friend,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce my arrival here, I have often been deſirous in my own ſpirit, at large to have writ to thee, but hitherto by a power above me, I have been hindered, and yet am, as to the particular aforeſaid; only now I thought it not only convenient to acquaint thee, but am thereunto compelled to tell thee, that meeting here with one of thoſe precious people called <hi>quakers,</hi> of which people thee and I at the Iſle of <hi>Ierſey</hi> had much talk of, and getting into my hands two Volumes of their printed papers, amounting to about ſeventeen hundred pages, I have with ſeriouſneſs of diſcourſe, and ſerious reading therein, been knock'd down off, or from my former legs, or ſtanding; and giving ſcope to my true teacher and guide, the light of God ſpeaking in my ſoul, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com at preſent dead to my fallen, or firſt natures reaſon, wit, wiſdom, and deſires, and alſo totally becom dead to my old buſling waies in the fleſh, and now in a great degree or meaſure, am ſtruct down dead to the very earth within me, and by that light which gloriouſly with in my ſoul hath ſhined round about my firſt, or corrupt nature within me, I am like <hi>Paul</hi> with aſtoniſhment and amazement, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. fallen down flat at the feet of Jeſus, and hearing a voice ſpeaking within me, to perſwade me for my good and benefit, to become willing to be guided and directed by the heavenly wiſdom of Jeſus my Anoynted; I have thereupon given up my ſelf wholly to be guided by his divine teachings ſhining within me, before which I now ſtand ready to give ear to what by it ſhall be told me, being willing and deſirous to have the ſcales fall further from the blinde eyes of my ſoul, that they may be further open'd; and that a <hi>power</hi> therewith may come in to my ſoul, from the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which may inable me in the ſtrength thereof, to redeem my loſt, and miſ-ſpent by-paſt precious time, and not now to conſult with fleſh and blood in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117964:6"/>my daily taking up the <hi>Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> and following him whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſhall by his call, or heavenly Divine voice within me, lead me.</p>
                  <p>I ſay, I am compelled from a power within me, at this preſent time, in brief to tell thee theſe things, and to require thee from God, to give ear to that true convincing light, that clearly ſpeaks in thy conſcience, and by the aſſiſtance thereof to ſtrive with the firſt, or fallen nature yet ruling in thy ſoul, and lay aſide that greatneſs of wit and earthly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that thou haſt attained to, and in that meaſure of Light that long ſince thou haſt received, withdraw into thy private Cloſet, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly meditate upon theſe brief lines. And being thou in my late converſing with thee, told me, thou hadſt read, or hadſt ſent me down from London moſt of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Books; Let me in love to thy ſoul, earneſtly intreat thee, with ſeriouſneſs to read over (ſtrong and tall in Chriſt) <hi>Iames Nayler,</hi> his ſheet of paper, intitled, <hi>Something fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in anſwer to</hi> John Jackſons <hi>book, called, Strength in weakneſs;</hi> (which <hi>Iohn Iackſon</hi> is my indeared friend, and old and long acquaintance, and a greater profeſſor of Religion now, then ever thou thy ſelf in all thy zeal once was; therefore in him thou mayeſt plainly read thy own condition) and that precious priſoner of the Lords in <hi>Northampton Goal, VVilliam Dewsbury,</hi> his two books, the firſt and excellenteſt of which is called, The diſcovery of the great enmity of the ſerpent againſt the ſeed of the woman: &amp; his other book is intituled, The diſcovery of mans Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn: and the Lord by his almighty power ſet them home to thy ſoul. I heartily deſire to return thee my hearty thanks for all thy kindneſs and tenderneſs manifeſted to me at Jerſey, in our paſſage from thence, and at thy own houſe: ſo with my hearty ſalutations preſented to thee, and all thy friends that were with me at thy houſe at Weymouth. I deſire to let thee know, that by my moral, honeſt, carefull, and induſtrious old Nurſe Elizabeth Crome (who by reaſon of ſhortneſs of money with me, I am forced and compelled to part with) I have writ thee a few lines in her behalf, intreating thy countenance and favourable reſpect to the old (and real ſerviceable to me in my great diſtreſs in Jerſey) woman; in caſe in things that are juſt and righteous before God, ſhe deſire thy favour, and what thee, or thy friend and mine, <hi>Edward</hi> (commonly called Lievtenant) <hi>Tucker,</hi> in that particular doth for her, I ſhal thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully look upon as actions done to thy ſouls</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From Dover-Caſtle, being a place wherein God hath more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then ever before, opened the eyes of my underſtanding, <date>the 5. day of the to moneth, 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Faithful, hearty, and real wel-wiſhing friend, <hi>Iohn Lilburn.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117964:6"/>
            <p>With which fore-mentioned main or principal thing that I have now to ſay, I thus proceed, and go on with it; &amp; here in the eſpecial preſence of the Lord declare, that by that preſent meaſure of light now born up in my underſtanding, and moving in my ſoul at this very time, I am here compelled to let the Reader (whoſoever he be) to know, that as I have long underſtood from my wife the original of my fore-going Letter to her, ſhe conveyed to the hands of <hi>Oliver Cromwel himſelf,</hi> and at his Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Law's deſire, <hi>Charls Fleetwood</hi> (my old, and ſomtimes much familiar greatly obliging friend) gave him a copy of it, and notwithſtanding the clear declarations of a ſincere (changed in meaſure) heart in the ſaid Letter, at the penning of which, I <hi>had then loſt all manner of ability to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with one grain of</hi> Machivel, <hi>or humane deceitful policy, having then the very dreadful, and aweful, immediate, convincing, judging, and burning up power of God upon my ſoul;</hi> yet upon my ſaid writing, and my wifes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, as aforeſaid, of my ſaid Letter, many and great jealouſies ariſe upon me at <hi>VVhite-hall,</hi> at the ſtrange politick contrivance of my (largely reputed by them) politique heart in my turning quaker, (of which I had ſeveral wayes exact information) which it ſeems out of humane fear, took that powerful impreſſion upon my poor weak wife, as that, as I judged by her Letters to me, troubled the poor afflicted Woman at the very heart, and compelled her by writing in a vehement manner, to preſs me to ſign ſuch an ingagement as <hi>George Fox</hi> did, (the Copy of which I have ſeen and read) and ſent it up to Oliver Cromwel to ſecure him from his pretended fears of my politick indeavouring to craw the temporal ſword againſt him; unto which for many reaſons ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving then no manner of freedom in the earth to do it (<hi>George Fox</hi> though even then a precious man in my eyes, his particular actions being no rules for me to walk by, unleſs I lived in the very ſame life and power of Spiritual injoyments that he did, and had the very ſelf-ſame motions in ſpirit from God, that led him to a freedom and ability to do ſuch, and the like particular actions) I therefore then ceaſed it, and did it not; and if I had then done it for my own particular human ends, as to avoid further perſecution, and the like, I had in ſo doing been an outſide phariſaical imitator, and the greateſt and baſeſt of hypocrites, which ſin alone is the height of Gods<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 24.51. Rev. 3.15, 16. See Mat. 6.5. &amp; 23.13, 14. Luk. 11, 44.46. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> abhorrance, for although I muſt before the Lord now truly avow, that the ſaid Letter was a true and faithful (without fraud or guile) declaration of as real and ſpirituall a power of God in its meaſure, ſeiſing upon my ſoul, for my conviction of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual blindneſs and ſinfulneſs, as ever ſeized upon <hi>Pauls,</hi> declared in the 9 of the <hi>Acts,</hi> or any mans that ever breathed upon earth, yet betwixt the Winter-ſtorms and fierce tempeſts of conviction, (or rather the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it) and the pleaſant Sunſhine, dewey, and ſpringing days of growth into a meaſure of refreſhment, there is a vaſt difference; and therefore then the true occaſion, or real ground of all outward war and humane buſling conteſt being not taken away, or abſolutely crucified or ſubdued at <hi>the very Root in my ſoul,</hi> if then I had ſigned ſuch an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117964:7"/>I <hi>had clearly gone beyond my ſouls then living and real attainments,</hi> and thereby ran preſumptuouſly and wickedly beyond my meaſure, and ſo had tempted the Lord my then preſent Leader, and ſpiritual guide, and abominably ſinned againſt him.</p>
            <p>But now in my already attained growing up meaſure, <hi>having the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental witneſs of God within my</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſelf,</hi> that I am already truly and really attained, in ſubſtantial, and witneſſed within me, real truth, with the young men in Chriſt, ſpoken of by the Apoſtle<note n="c" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>John, to a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or degree, in overcoming the wicked one within me,</hi> ſo that now I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to witneſs in truth and righteouſnes, <hi>that the true grounds or reall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of all outward wars, and all carnal buſtings, and all fleſhly ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivings within me, is in a very large meaſure, or degree, become dead or crucified with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me:</hi> wen true grounds &amp; real occaſions, of all the outward iron and ſteel ſword war in the world, and all the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cked and fleſhly fore-runners of it and dependants upon it, <hi>truly riſeth from its fountain, the raging power of ſin, or luſt within,</hi> in carnal, and unregenerated, unſanctified, and unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (before God) mens hearts, as is plainly &amp; truly witneſſed by the apoſtle<note n="d" place="margin">Jam. 4.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>James</hi> in theſe words, <hi>From whence comes wars and fightings among you? come they not hence, even of your luſts, that war in your members? ye luſt, and have not; ye kill, and deſire to have, and cannot obtain; ye fight and war, yet ye have not, becauſe ye ask not. Ye ask, and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſs that you may conſume it upon your luſts. Ye</hi> Adulterers and Adultereſſes, <hi>know you not that the friendſhip of the world is enmity with God: whoſoever therefore will be a friend to the world</hi> (that ſpiritual Kingdom of Satan in unſanctified mens ſouls) is the enemy of God.</p>
            <p>And therefore Chriſt, the true Lord of the ſoul, and the true Head-Maſter, and King of that heavenly ſpiritual kingdome (as the Devil or Prince of the air, is the Head-Maſter, King, or God of the Kingdom of this world, in the hearts of the children of unſanctified, and unjuſtified, diſobedient<note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 2.2.3.5, &amp; 6.11. &amp; 2 Cor. 4.4. Jam. 1.13, 14, 15. Joh. 12.3. &amp; 16.11. Rom. 6.16.20. &amp; 2 Tim. 2.26. &amp; 2 Pet. 2.19. &amp; 1. Joh. 3.8.10.</note> men) that he hath provided for all redeemed, ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, juſtified and righteous<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 22, 23. &amp; 8.1, 2, 3, 4. Rom. 14.17. &amp; 15.13, 14. &amp; 1 Cor. 4.20. &amp; 2 Cor. 4 6. Gal. 5.22, 23, 24. Eph. 5 7, 8, 9. Heb. 12.22, 23. &amp; 1 Joh. 1.5, 6, 7. Rev. 6.14, 15, 16, 17 &amp; 21.3, 4.22, 23. &amp; 22.1, 2, 3, 4. Iſa. 60.19, 20, 21.</note> ſouls, declares at his very anſwer before <hi>Pilate</hi> for his life, and ſaith, <hi>My Kingdome is not of this world, if my king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom were of this world, then would my ſervants fight that</hi> I <hi>ſhould not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Jews; but now is my kingdom not from</hi>
               <note n="[g]" place="margin">Joh. 18.36.</note> 
               <hi>hence;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was when <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed this ſpiritual King, Chriſt, into the hands of his murdering enemies, and that his ſervant <hi>Simon</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Joh 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſtretched out his hand, and drew his ſword, and ſtroke a ſervant of the High Prieſts, and ſmote off his ear; that this ſpiritual King, Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, cured the wounded man, although he was his<note n="i" place="margin">Luke 22.50 51.</note> enemy, &amp; comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his ſervant <hi>Peter</hi> to put up his ſword again in his place, further ſaying to him, <hi>For all they that take the</hi> Sword [mark it well] <hi>ſhall periſh with the</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 26.51, 52, 53. ſee Gen. 9.6. Rev. 13.10.</note> Sword: <hi>Thinkest thou that</hi> I <hi>cannot now pray to my</hi> Father, <hi>and he ſhall preſently give me more then twelve</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">A conſtituted full <hi>Roman</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, at this time as I remember the <hi>Roman</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be commonly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 7 or 8000. men.</note> 
               <hi>Legions of Angells.</hi> And therefore all the whole Laws of his inward and ſpiritual Kingdome, are made in quite oppoſition againſt the Laws of the meer glorious out-ſide king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the God and Prince of this world; unto which two <hi>Maſters,</hi> or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117964:7"/>
               <hi>Kings, or Law-givers, it is impoſſible for any man in the world, or upon this globy earth, to be a ſervant to them both, at one &amp; the ſame</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>24. Luke 16.13.</note> 
               <hi>time, but he that commits ſin is the ſervant of ſin, and ſo the ſervant of the</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Joh. 8.34.41, 42, 44. Rom. 6.16. &amp; 2 Per. 2.19. &amp; 1 John 3.8.10.</note> 
               <hi>devil; and he that is the ſervant of ſin, is free from righteouſneſs, and ſo from being a ſervant or ſubject unto</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 6.17, 18, 20, 21, 22, 23 1 Joh. 1.6. &amp; cap. 3.3, 4, 5, 6, 9. &amp; 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 18, 19. Joh. 7.17. &amp; 8.31, 32. &amp; 9.31. &amp; 12.26. &amp; 14.15.21, 23, 24. &amp; 15.4.7.10.14.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And therefore the Spirit of Chriſt, this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual inſide-King, dwelling in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> declares, <hi>that there is no fellowſhip betwixt righteouſneſs and unrighteouſneſs, nor no communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt light and darkneſs, nor no concord betwixt Chriſt and Belial, nor no har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony betwixt the true beleever</hi> (that knows<note n="p" place="margin">Joh. 17.3.</note> God) <hi>and the infidel,</hi> (and ſuch are all they that truly knows not<note n="q" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4, 5. Se Tit. 1.16. Ex. 5.2. Pſal. 79.6. Jer. 10.25. Ro. 1.19.21. Eph. 4.17, 8, 19.</note> God.) <hi>And there he further demands: what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? for ye are</hi> (ſaith he to the true knowers of God in <hi>Corinth</hi>) <hi>the Temple of the living God, as God hath</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Levit. 26.12.</note> 
               <hi>ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people; wherefore come out from among them, and be ye</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Iſa. 52.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſeparate ſaith the Lord, and touch not</hi> (mark it well) <hi>the unclean thing, and I will receive you, and will be a Father unto</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Jer. 31.1.</note> 
               <hi>you, and ye ſhal be my Sons and Daughters ſaith the Lord</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Almighty.</hi> And therefore it is, that the very ſame Divine Spirit that dwells in this Spiritual King Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ſpeaking in the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi> requires all his Spiritual and true Subjects, <hi>not to love the world, neither the things that are in the world,</hi> for, <hi>if any man love the world,</hi> (that Kingdom of Satan the Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as) <hi>the luſts of the Fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world; and the world</hi> (and the vanities and empty pleaſures of it) <hi>paſſeth away, and the luſts thereof; but he that doth the will of God, abideth for</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, the contrariety is ſo great betwixt the foreſaid two Kings and Maſters, that whatſoever in the King, or Ruler in the Kingdom of the world, (or falne, or unrenewed man) and the Subjects thereof, <hi>is eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med highly, or excellent, is an abomination in the ſight of</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Luke 16.15. See chap 6.24, 25, 26. Mar. 13.13. Joh. 5.41.44. &amp; 7.17, 18. &amp; 8.50.54. &amp; 11.41, 43. &amp; 15.19. &amp; 16.35.</note> 
               <hi>God:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Spiritual King, having purchaſed all his Subjects and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with a glorious price (as the greateſt demonſtration of love) of his own blood, by his ſpiritual Command requires them not to be the ſervants of<note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.23.</note> men, but to glorifie him both in body and<note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20. ſee chap. 3.16, 17 &amp; 2 Cor. 2.5.15.17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſoul; and therefore his grown up ſervant <hi>Paul,</hi> declares himſelf to be no <hi>man plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> avowing himſelf, that if he were a <hi>man-pleaſer,</hi> he ſhould, nor could not be the ſervant of<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 1.10. ſee 4.3.9, 10.11. &amp; 5. 1 Col. 2.8.30.22.</note> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore the ſame Apoſtle, by the infallible ſpirit of the Lord, requires the Spiritual Subjects of this Spiritual King Jeſus, to preſent their bodies a living ſacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which (ſaith he) is your reaſonable ſervice; and be not conformed to this world (the kingdom of the prince of darkneſs) but be ye transformed by the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your minde, that ye may prove what is that good, &amp; acceptable, &amp; perfect will of<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 22.1, 2.</note> God; and therefore when any man becomes a ſpiritual Subject of this Spiritual King Chriſt, and dwells in him, he becomes a <hi>new creature,</hi> &amp; old things in him are paſt away, and all things in him are becom<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>new, ſpiritual,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſavory;</hi> yea even his very thoughts, &amp; his words
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117964:8"/>are found few and divine, his behaviour righteous and ſolid, his deeds upright, and free like God from all reſpect of<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 3.34.37, 39, 40, 41, 45, 46, 48. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.25 31, 32, 33. and 7.12, 13. and 23, 3.5, 6, 7.8, 9.10. Mark 12.14. Luk. 20, 21. Act 10.34, 35. Deu. 10 17. Eſth. 3.2 5, 6. Job 32.21, 22. Prov. 10.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28.21. Rom. 2.11. and 1 Cor. 2.16. and 15 33 Gal 2.6. Eph. 4 29. and 5.4. and 6.9. Phil. 2 5. Col. 3.5.8, 15.16. &amp; 4.6. 1 Tim. 1.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 Tim. 1 7.13. and 4.3. Tit. 1.9.17. and 2.1, 2.8. Jam. 2.1. to 10. and 5.12. and 1 Pet. 1.15, 16, 17. and 4.12. and 2 John 9, 10, 11.</note> perſons: and although there be ſuch a perfect and abſolute contrariety betwixt all the laws &amp; conſtitutions of theſe two Kings or Maſters, and a continuall and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall war betwixt the Subjects thereof, yet the weapons of the warfare of Chriſts Spiritual, Heavenly, and glorious Kingdom, handled and uſed by his Servants and true Subjects, who although they do walk in the fleſh, yet do they not war after the fleſh, and therefore their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of warfare are not carnall, but mighty through God; to the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down of ſtrong holds, caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, and bringeth into captivity every thought to the obedience of<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 10.3, 4, 5.</note> Chriſt: The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of Proof of theſe Spiritual warring Subjects and Souldiers of this ſpiritual glorious King, <hi>is to have their loynes girt about with truth, &amp; having on them the Breſt-plate of righteouſneſs, and their feet ſhod with the preparation of the Gospel of peace; above all, taking the Shield of Faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they ſhall be able to quench the fiery-darts of the wicked, and taking the Helmet of Salvation, and the Sword of the Spirit, which is the word of</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eph 6.13, 14, 15, 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>God;</hi> which Spiritual Sword, or Word of God, <hi>is quick and powerful, and ſharper then any two edged Sword, piercing, even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joints and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart; neither is there any creature that is not manifeſt in his ſight,</hi> (who is this Spiritual ſharp Sword, or eternall and everlaſting Word of God that indures for ever) <hi>but all things are naked and opened to the eyes of him with whom we have to</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 4.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>do.</hi> With which Spirituall Sword this ſpiritual conquering Lord and King, pricked and wounded to the very heart three thouſand of his enemies at once, by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his ſingle Spiritual Souldier, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> which made them bitterly to cry out for a Plaiſter, and a Phyſician to heal and cure<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 2.37.41.</note> them: which ſpiritual Sword is the only and alone weapon that this glorious, conquering, ſpiritual King uſeth to fight withall againſt all enemies, the powers of the Prince of Darkneſs of this world; and with which only and alone he conquereth and<note n="i" place="margin">Rev. 1.16. and 2.12.16. and 19.15.21. Hoſ. 6.7.</note> overcometh carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of any kinde whatſoever, having no place, nor being of no uſe at all in his ſpiritual Kingdom, for his Subjects are to love their enemies, to do good unto their haters, and to reſiſt or requite their evill with<note n="k" place="margin">Matt. 5.39, 40, 44, 45, 56.</note> good, and to dwell in love towards all men, as the God of love himſelf dwells in<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 6.10. and 1 Theſ. 3 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 5.14, 15. 1 Joh. 4.16, 17.</note> love, and to be holy as God is<note n="m" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15, 16.</note> holy, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as he is<note n="n" place="margin">Matt. 5.48.</note> perfect, and therefore not in the leaſt to draw tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral weapons againſt their enemies; for among the true and real Saints of the Lord in the mountain of the Lord, where the Lord himſelf is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ſoul-teacher and inſtructer of his people and Subjects in his own waies; there all the temporal ſwords are to be beat into plowſhares, and their earthly ſpears into pruning-hooks, &amp; no more uſing of carnal ſwords, or ſo much as learning of earthly war, is to be exerciſed amongſt<note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 2.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> them, but they are to walk in the pure, holy, &amp; peaceable light of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117964:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord, which ſhal &amp; wil lead the ſanctified, juſtified and redeemed ſoul to advance, or ſet up the innocent, harmleſs, peaceable lamb-like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or ſeed of Chriſt, to become Lord and King in the heart, of, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Lyon-like warring; devouring, and deſtroying-wicked nature of the ſerpent, the devil, &amp; ſatan, within man, yea in the Goſpel-mount of God, or the ſpiritual kingdom of Chriſt (under the Goſpel-diſpenſation) the habitation of the true Saint of God; <hi>The wolf ſhal dwel with the lamb, and the leopard ſhal ly down with the kid, &amp; the calf, &amp; the young lyon, &amp; the fatling together, &amp; a little child ſhal lead them. And the cow and the bear ſhal feed, their young ones ſhall lye down together. And the lyon ſhall eat ſtraw like the oxe. And the ſucking-child ſhall play on the hole of the aſp, and the weaned child ſhall pui his hand on the Cockatrice Den. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eſa. 11. 6, 7, 8, 9. &amp; 65.25.</note> 
               <hi>mountain, ſaith God; For the earth ſhall be full of the Knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea. Yea, they ſhall be far from</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Eſa. 54.14. &amp; 66.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Oppreſſion: Yea, and violence ſhall no more be heard in the Land;</hi> (of the ſpirituall Kingdom, inhabited by the ſpirituall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or true Saints of Chriſt, nor) <hi>waſting, nor deſtruction within their borders; but they ſhall call their wall ſalvation; and their Gates Praiſe. The Sun</hi> (or borrowed humane Lights, or Rudimentall Ordinances) <hi>ſhall be no more thy Light</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>by day, neither for brightneſs ſhall the Moon give Light unto thee: but the Lord ſhall be unto thee an everlaſting Light, and thy God thy glory. Thy Sun ſhall no more go downe, neither ſhall thy Moon withdraw it ſelf, for the Lord ſhall be thine everlaſting Light, and the dayes of thy mourning ſhall be ended. Thy people ſhall be all Righteous, they ſhall inherit the Land for ever, the branch of my planting, the work of my hands, that I may be glorified. A little one ſhall become a thouſand, &amp; a ſmall one a ſtrong nation; I the Lord wil haſten it in his</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Eſa. 60.18, 19, 20, 21, 22. See ch. 40.19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 25, 26. Rev. 7.14, 15, 16, 17. &amp; 21.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.10.11.22, 23, 24, &amp; 22.1, 2 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all which conſideration, I ſay, I have now the faithfull and true witneſs in my own ſoul, that the Lord himſelf is become within me, the Teacher of my ſoul, and inabler of me to walk in a meaſure of his pure wayes and paths; yea, and ſo clear a teacher within me, is he alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy become unto me, as that I with confidence beleeve my inward Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſhal never now more be removed into a corner; but is, and ſhall be as a continual voice ſpeaking in my ears; <hi>This is the way, walk in</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Eſa. 30.20, 21. ſee ch. 24.18, 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35.7, 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 42.2, 3, 4.7. &amp; 44 3 &amp; 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 54.13. Prov. 6.22, 23. Pſ 37.31. Deu. 18.15, 16.18, 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34.6. Jer. 24.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 31.31, 32, 33, 34. and 32.14, 15. Eze. 11.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34.22, 23.24, 25, 26.27 <hi>&amp;</hi> 36.24, 25, 26, 27. and 37.22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28. Joel 2.28, 29. Matt. 11.27. Luk. 10.22. Joh. 1.5 9 12 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.41.45. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.37, 38, 39. and 9.5.39. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.7.9, 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.9, 10.25.22.12.35, 36, 46.48. and 14.16, 17, 18, 19.23 26. and 15.5.15. and 16, 7, 8.13, 14.26, 27, 28. Act. 1.4. and 2.4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6, 17, 18. Rom. 10.7, 8, 9, 10. Gal. 1.15, 16. Heb. 8.7, 8, 9 10, 11. and 10.16.19, 20. and 1 Joh. 2.2.20.27, and 3.24 and 4.13. and 5.10 20 ſee Act. 17.27, 28.31. and 26.16.18. Rom. 1.19.21. and 2.15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6, 27, 28, 39. and 1 Cor. 7.19. and 2 Cor. 2.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4 6. Gal. 3.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.5, 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.15. Phil. 3.3. Col. 2.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Tim. 4.10. Tit. 2.11, 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Joh, 1.5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>it:</hi> By which divine teaching I am now daily taught to dye to ſin, and led up by it into living power, to be raiſed up, and inabled to live in a pure meaſure of Righteouſneſs; and by which inward ſpiritual teachings, I am, I ſay again, led up into power in Chriſt, by which I particularly can, and do hereby witneſs, that I am already dead, or crucified, to the very occaſions, and real grounds of all outward wars, and carnal ſword-fightings <hi>&amp;</hi> fleſhly buſlings and conteſts; and that therefore I confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117964:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>now believe, I ſhall never hereafter be an uſer of a temporal ſword more, nor a joyner with thoſe that ſo do. And this I do here ſolemnly declare, not in the leaſt to avoid perſecution, or for any politick ends of my own, or in the leaſt, for the ſatisfaction of the fleſhly wils of any of my great adverſaries, or for ſatisfying the carnal will of my poor weak, afflicted wife; but by the ſpecial movings and compulſions of God now upon my ſoul, am I in truth and righteouſneſs compelled thus to declare, that ſo I may take away from my adverſaries all their fig leaf-covers, or pretences of their continuing of my every way unjuſt bonds; And thereby, if yet I muſt be an impriſoned ſufferer, it may from this day forward, be for the truth, as it is in Jeſus: Which truth I witneſs to be truly profeſſed and practiſed by the ſavourieſt of people called <hi>quakers:</hi> And to this my preſent declaration, which I exceedingly long and earneſtly deſire to have in print, and for which I know that I can chearfully and aſſuredly lay down my life, if I be called to witneſs the truth of it, I ſubſcribe my outward name</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my innocent, and every way cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs captivity in <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> the place of my ſouls delightful and contentful abode, where I have really and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially found that which my ſoul many yeers hath ſought diligently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and with unſatisfied longingneſs, thirſted to in joy, this preſent firſt day of the week, being <date>the 4th of the 3d. month, 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>IOHN LILBVRN,</hi> the new, or inward ſpiritual name, no man knowes but he that hath it.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117964:9"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX TO This ſecond <hi>Edition</hi> of my foregoing <hi>Reſurrection Declaration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Appendix to this ſecond Edition of my foregoing <hi>Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Declaration,</hi> directed to the ſerious and ſingle-hearted Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whom I deſire to let know, that in my reading of my own foregoing lines in the firſt Impreſſion, I found divers miſtakes or errors, committed by the Printer, the <hi>greateſt of which</hi> I judged to be in the very laſt line of it, in the Date of the Yeer, which he hath made 1655. <hi>but in my Copy it is</hi> 1656. which, with all the reſt of the miſtakes that I can finde, I have with my own hand amended in a printed Book, and ſent it up again the ſecond time to be impreſſed. And being it was my former order it ſhould have no Title page at all, but the Title prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cloſe in the very ſame page that the matter begins in, that ſo the Reader might have it at as cheap a rate as its poſſibe by the Book-ſeller to be afforded him. And being I finde in the ſecond Impreſſion there will be two or three pages of white paper, I am therefore extraordinary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to fill them up at leaſt with two late Epiſtles, which I judge very pertinent for my old, affectionate and faithful (though ſtumbling, and offended at me) friends, to ſee and read, that ſo they may more fully ſee and read, that I have not of late taken up my preſent principles without grounds and foundations <hi>in the Rock of ages, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that eternal and everlaſting word of God, and divine and heavenly light of the world, or fallen and ſinful man, in whom was, and is life; and the light was, and is the life of</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>man; which light, or life, is the living, quickning, holy, or tender part of man. VVhich everlaſting word of God, by whom all things were</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 1.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>made, I aver, is the divine and true light, that,</hi> in meaſure, <hi>inlightneth the ſoul of every man whatſoever, that cometh into the</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 1.9. and 8.12. and 12.36.46.</note> 
               <hi>world; and is that reproving, judging; and condemning witneſs of God, and for God, that reſides in the dark hearts of Iew and Greek, circumciſion and uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, Barbarian, Scythian, bond and free; where the light Chriſt is all, and in all, and died for</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 16.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 26. chap. 3.19.36. and 8.24. Col. 3.10, 11. Eph. 1.23. and 4.6.10. Rom. 5.8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and 1 Cor. 15.22. and 2 Cor. 5.14. Col. 1.20. and 1 Tim. 2.4.6. and 4.10. Tit. 2.11, 12. and 1 Ioh. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>all, and infallibly leads all into the light of life, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the light within them, love it, obey it, and perſeveringly abide in it; and condemnation it is to all and every one of thoſe that reject and deſpiſe it:</hi> And that he hath indowed my ſoul with an underſtanding, flowing from a fountain of light, life, and power, able to make out to the leaſt grain of muſtard-ſeed (or meaſure) of ſpiritual underſtanding, <hi>thoſe things which I have already attained to;</hi> the Copy of the firſt of which two letters, take in theſe following words.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117964:10"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> 
                        <date>the 18th. day of the 3d. Moneth, 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>For his beloved Friend, <hi>Elizabeth Hunniwood,</hi> Wife to <hi>Edward Hunni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> at her Houſe at <hi>Eventon,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Elmſtead</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> theſe deliver.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Beloved Friend,</hi> Elizabeth Hunniwood,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe late friendly viſit of me by thy Husband, in thy Fathers Name, and thy own, hath to me demonſtrated a continuation of a meaſure of that former greatneſs of friendly and indeared familiarity, that hath been betwixt thy Father, <hi>Iohn Maynard, thy ſelf, and me;</hi> and having the conveniency of this Bearer, <hi>Martha Gardner,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Robert Gardner</hi> thy neighbour, and Siſter to my Civil-Marſhal, or now Goaler, <hi>VVilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Spicer,</hi> I have freedom in my own ſpirit by her, to viſit thee thus with a few of my lines, and in them to incloſe two of my late printed books, (in which there are ſome few <hi>Printers</hi> errors) one of which is for thy ſelf, the other for thy Husband, in the ſerious reading of which, thou wilt meet with the <hi>clear declarations</hi> of the Lords gracious, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing ſhinings in, by his <hi>divine light,</hi> of late into my ſoul.</p>
                  <p>That ripeneſs and greatneſs of wit that is in thee, may, it may be, lead thee out to judge them fooliſhneſs; but let me in the wiſdom of God (<hi>to which all mans excellenteſt of wiſdom is meer</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.20, 25, 27. &amp; chap. 2.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, to the end. and 12.3. &amp; 15.50. Rom. 8.7, 8, 9, 10. Gal. 4.3, 6. Jam. 4.4. &amp; 1 Joh. 2.15, 16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>fooliſhneſs</hi>) truly tell thee, there is no other way given under heaven to know the will,<note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 1.12.</note> or to have revealed to the ſoul the minde of the Eather, <hi>but by hearing, heeding, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying, loving, and following the light of Chriſt ſhining in the ſoul;</hi> which light of Chriſt in its meaſure, is <hi>that grace, favour, or love of God that bringeth</hi> (ſheweth, or diſcovereth) <hi>ſalvation, that hath appeared to all</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 2.11, 12. ſee Rom. 15.18. &amp; 1 Cor. 15.22. &amp; 2 Cor. 15.14, 15. Eph. 1.23. &amp; 4.6, io. Col. 1.20. &amp; 3.11, &amp; 1 Tim. 2.4, 6. &amp; 4.10. &amp; 1 Joh. 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>men, teaching them, or us, to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea, Chriſt is that true light, <hi>that inlightneth every man</hi> (in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) <hi>that cometh into the world;</hi> which divine and heavenly light, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the dark hearts of faln man, <hi>although the darkneſs is not able to fathome or comprehend</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Joh. 1.5.9. &amp; 5.40.</note> 
                     <hi>it;</hi> but to as many as receive it, and perſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly follow and abide in it, <hi>it leads them ſtep by ſtep up into a living pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to become the ſons of God; yea, to be freed from darkneſs, and heart-blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to walk in the light of life, where there is no occaſion of ſtumbling, but where the light is as clear as the bright ſhining of a candle; yea, as the light that is in God himſelf, in whom is no darkneſs at</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Joh. 8.12. &amp; 11.9. &amp; 12.36, 46. &amp; 2 Cor. 4.6. Eph. 5.8, 12. &amp; 1 Joh. 1.5, 6, 7. Luk. 11.36. ſee Joh. 14.15, 16, 17, 26. &amp;. 16.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 25. Matt. 11.27. Luk. 10.22. Act. 4.12. &amp; 10.43. &amp; 13.38, 39.</note> 
                     <hi>all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whether thou canſt receive any thing of this yea or nay, it will not add much to me, nor diminiſh nothing at all from me; but know thou, <hi>my old beloved friend,</hi> that all thy preſent greatneſs in the world, and all thy excellencie and quickneſs of wit, and meer outſide greatneſs of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, notional profeſſion, are but all as a blaſt of empty uncomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded wind, that certainly and ſwiftly paſſeth away, <hi>but the light of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> indures for ever, and makes infallibly &amp; compleatly happy that ſoul that minds and loves it, and patiently and abidingly</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Joh. 6.40, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 46, 47, 51, 54, 56, 57, 60, 63, 66. &amp; 7.17. &amp; 8.12, 30, 31. &amp; 12.26, 36. &amp; 13.35. &amp; 14.15, 21, 23, 24. &amp; 15.1, 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 12, 4, 16 Acts 5.42. Heb. 3.14. &amp; 5.9. &amp; 1 Joh. 2.6, 10, 14, 17, 24, 27, 28. &amp; 3.6, 14, 24. &amp; 2 Joh. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>follows it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117964:10"/>
                  <p>Yea, and on the contrary hand, <hi>is the eternal, ſure, and certain condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all thoſe that deſpiſe, reject and contemn it, according to that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true ſaying of the</hi> Spirit of<note n="g" place="margin">Joh. 3.19.</note> God: <hi>And this is condemnation, that ſight is come into the world,</hi> (the hearts of falne men, infidels, or unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers) <hi>and men loved darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds were evil: and therefore,</hi> there<note n="h" place="margin">Verſ. 36.</note> it is further ſaid, <hi>he that believeth on the Son,</hi> (the true light, and eternal and everlaſting word of<note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> God) <hi>hath ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life; and he that believeth not the Son,</hi> (the true and infallible light of God in the ſoul of every man) <hi>ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him:</hi> And further, ſaith the light himſelf, (<hi>that lighteth every man that cometh into the</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Joh. 1.9.</note> 
                     <hi>world</hi>) to the wicked, and hard-hearted, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Jews, <hi>ye will not come to me that ye might have</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Joh. 5 40.</note> 
                     <hi>life;</hi> although he plainly told them, the true and real way for them to be the children of light and life, <hi>was by their believing in the</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Joh. 12.36, 46.</note> 
                     <hi>light;</hi> and therefore he requires and commands <hi>them to take heed that the light in them be not</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 11.34, 35. ſee Matt. 6.22, 23. Joh. 9.5. &amp; 11.9, 10. &amp; 12 35.36. ſee Rom. 2.19. &amp; 2 Cor. 4.4. Eph. 5.8, 11. Col. 1.13. &amp; 1 Theſ. 5.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>darkneſs,</hi> which it ſoon becomes to be, when the light which leads up to purity, holineſs and righteouſneſs, is rejected, contemned, and deſpiſed, and the voice or motions of the Serpent in the heart, is minded, heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to, and followed; which voice or motions of the ſerpent in the heart, leads out into ſlaying the motions of <hi>the juſt</hi> within; yea, even into the ſpiritual death and rebellion againſt God, by which the creature in time comes to be heart-blinded, and ſo by degrees to be given over to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſenſe, and to have the conſcience, of tender part of it, <hi>ſeared with a hot iron, ſo that it becomes paſt feeling,</hi> ſo that the ſoul thereby comes, yea, even to be void of common underſtanding, and deſtitute of naturall affections, know nothing, but naturally<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 1.21, 23, 24, 25, 28, 31. &amp; 2 Cor. 4.4, 6. Eph. 2. i, 2, 3. &amp; 4.17, 18, 19, &amp; 1 Theſ. 4.5. &amp; 1 Tim. 4.1, 2. Tit. 1.16.</note> as a bruit<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 1.31. Jude 10.</note> beaſt.</p>
                  <p>My Wife and Babes are lately come down to live at <hi>Dover</hi> Town, but ſhe being there abſent now from me, I can onely in my own name ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute thee and thy Husband: If thou haſt any freedom to write to me, I ſhould be glad to hear from thee: And ſo in my Light and Life I reſt:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From my innocent, and every way cauſeleſs Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> 
                        <date>this firſt day of the week, being the 18. day of the 3d. month, 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Thine, as thou art one in love and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to that true light, that now in much brightneſs and clearneſs ſhines in the hearts of the waſhed, purged, redeemed, ſanctified, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſons of God, (reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called <hi>quakers</hi>) <hi>IOHN LILBVRNE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:117964:11"/>
                  <head>The Copy of the forementioned ſecond Letter, take in theſe following words.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Dover-Caſtle, <date>the 25. of the 3d. month, 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>For <hi>Robert Barrington,</hi> one of the members of the meer outſide, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting without life or power, <hi>VVater-Baptiſts</hi> Congregation in Dover in Kent.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Robert Barrington,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BEſides thoſe many and wrangling Encounters and Aſſaults, that I have of late had, <hi>from ſeveral of thy meer outſide Form,</hi> which they profeſs <hi>without life or power, true Adminiſtrator, or right Subject,</hi> having alſo perverted that ſometimes Ordinance, or Divine Inſtitution of God <hi>(VVater-baptiſm)</hi> from its primitive forerunning end of Chriſt, the real <hi>ſum and ſubſtance of all Shadows, Figures, Rudiments, outſide-Ordinances, and Types;</hi> yea, and of all the Prophets (whereof John the Baptiſt was one) Adminiſtrations; to make it now all in all, as though damnation were the abſolute portion of him that hath by faith never ſo much communion in the ſpirit with the ſouls true ſpiritual food, the ſpiritual Jeſus Chriſt, the true and real light of the world, (or of all falne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde) if he be not water-dipt in your meer empty, outſide, vain, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall, humane, invented (as you uſe it) form, which you falſely and untruly call <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> I ſay I have, beſides all aforeſaid, from thee of late received by <hi>VV. S.</hi> one of thy own Congregation, a Meſſage to this very effect:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That by my turning</hi> Quaker, (as we are commonly called) <hi>I had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore, although my late condition, or that firſt beginning of growing meaſure, (to which through riches of mercy I have attained to) hath much required of me a ſilent, ſtill, quiet, home-dwelling, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient waiting<note n="r" place="margin">Eſa. 30.7, 15, 18. Act. 1.3, 4, 5, 8. Luk. 24.49 &amp; 2 Pet. 4.10, 11.</note> upon God, (as having the declaration of a promiſe of bleſſedneſs annexed to it, to be upon all thoſe that ſo do) rather then to ſpend my then preſent ſtock, or attained to portion, in running out in Pen-conteſts and controverſies, though for truth; but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding now to take away thy reproach from the truth, and thy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and continued blaſphemy (as my often information tells me) by thy ſelf caſt upon it, I do hereby truly tell thee, I have of late within theſe very few dayes, been in ſpirit much compelled, meerly for the truths ſake, (to which, according to my meaſure, to the very death I am bound, as I am called to bear witneſs to) to indeavour to vindicate it from the ſaid reproaches: And whileſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I was ſtrongly meditating with the Rock of my ſtrength, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt [the pure inlightner of my ſoul] is handed out unto me, a neceſſity to reviſe anew for the Preſs my foregoing Declaration; unto which, by way of part of an Appendix, I have had much impreſſion upon my ſpirit, to inſert a few ſubſtantial lines unto thee in it, in truths behalf, purely flowing from the dictates
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117964:11"/>of that meaſure of Light, life and power; now brought forth, and born up in my underſtanding, by which I am in a meaſure enabled, truly and really to know<note n="s" place="margin">Luk. 24.44.45. comp. with Joh. 20.21, 22. Act. 1.3, 4, 5.8. &amp; 2.4. &amp; 11.34, 35.38.43, 44, 45, 46. But ſee 1 Cor. 2.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. Eph. 4.10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3, 3. &amp; 1 Joh. 8.10, 27. &amp; 5.20. &amp; 2 John 7.8.</note> the things of God, as they are in Jeſus; and by which I am guided at this preſent time thus further and <hi>ſubſtantially</hi> to expreſs my ſelf to thee, <hi>Robert Barrington, viz.</hi> That the very, firſt Principle of all true Religion, is the Light of Chriſt; without the real knowledge, embracing, and being guided by which, I do here in the ſtrength, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and power of the Lord, <hi>(my light and life)</hi> aver, thou knoweſt, <hi>nor canſt not truly know without it, any thing of God at all; no, no more then the devills know</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 8.28, 29. Mark. 1.23, 24, 25. &amp; 3. 11, 12 &amp; 5.2.5, 6, 7. Luk. 4.33, 34, 35.41. &amp; 8.27, 28. &amp; 10.17. Act. 16.16, 17, 18. &amp; 19.13, 14, 15, 16. Ja. 2.19.</note> 
                     <hi>acknowledge, and confeſs; or, then  the high Prieſts, the Scribes, and Phariſees, or Iews did know, that put Chriſt to death;</hi> who not only had the Scriptures commonly and publikely read amongſt them, but alſo many of them <hi>beleeved the words ſpoken by the ſound of the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>hly mouth of Chriſt,</hi> and yet not minding the meaſure of Chriſt within them, he tells them plainly; <hi>they were of their Father the</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 13.26, 27, 28. ch. 3.12, 13, 14, 15. &amp; 4.1, 2.5, 6.11, 12.17, 18. and 5.17, 18.21.28.40. &amp; 6.13, 14, 15. and 7.1.37, 38.51, 52.54.57.59. compared with Joh. 1.32, 33. &amp;. 5.16.18.24, 25.28, 29.32.38, 39, 40.46. &amp; 6.56, 57.60.63.66. &amp; 7.26.28.31.45, 46.49. &amp; 8.26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, to 48.</note> 
                     <hi>devil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore I further lay down this as a poſitive Poſition, which through the ſtrength of God, I ſhall not only be able, by the Letter, or Witneſs without me, <hi>viz. the Scripture, or Declaration</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 1.1. Acts 1.1. &amp; 10.37. &amp; 13.32. &amp; 15.35. &amp; 17.23. &amp; 20.27. &amp; 1 Cor. 15.1.3. Gal. 1.16. &amp; 1 Joh. 1.3.5. Rev. 19.13.</note> 
                     <hi>of the word of God,</hi> clearly to maintain againſt the ableſt man whatſoever, that ſpeaks with a tongue that can, or ſhall oppoſe it; but alſo to lay down my very life, by vertue of that meaſure of living power or life, already raiſed up, or dwelling in me, for the defence of it: That is to ſay,</p>
                  <p>That the very principle of all true religion is, [without the knowledge of which, no man whatſoever can truly know himſelf, or his own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt heart, (<hi>which is above the knowledge of</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Jer. 17.9; 10. &amp; 11.20. Gen. 6.5. &amp; 8.21. Deut. 11.16. &amp; 1 Sam. 16.17. and 1 Chron. 28.9. &amp; 29.17. &amp; 2 Chr. 32.31. Pſal. 7.9. &amp; 10, 3.6.11. &amp; 14.1. &amp; 44.21. &amp; 64.5, 6, 7. &amp; 139.1. Prov. 16.1, 2. Rom 8.27. &amp; 1 Joh. 2.20.27. &amp; ch. 1.5, 6, 7. &amp; 4.20. Rev. 2.23. &amp; 3.7. Joh. 16.6, 7.11.27. and 1 Cor. 2.11.14, 15, 16. Eph. 5.8.13. Heb. 4 12, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>man, or all mans excellent eſt of</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 11.25. &amp; 13.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.15, 16. Mark 4.11, 12.34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.32. Luk. 8.10: <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.34 <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.41, 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.8.11.15, 16.20.25, 26, 27.31, 32.45. Joh. 7.26.48, 49. Act. 3.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7.13.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.27, 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Cor. 1.20, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8. ſee Eſa. 2.12, 13.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 48.18.20.25, 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 47.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 50.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59.10, 11. Joh. 9.39, 40, 41. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.22.24. Jam. 2.5, 6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>wiſdom</hi>) or the<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 11.27. Luk. 10.22. Joh. 1.9.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. 35, 36.46. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Cor. 2.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.3. Mat. 16.17. Act. 4.12. and 10.43. and 13.38.39.</note> Lord, or ever offer up any ſacrifice to the Lord, acceptable<note n="g" place="margin">Joh. 4.23, 24. Rom. 8.7, 8.15.26, 27. and 1 Cor. 12.3. and 15.50. Gal. 4.6. Eph. 3.3. Jam. 4.4. and 1 Pet. 2.5. and 1 Joh. 1.6, 7. and 2.15. and 3.6.8, 9, 10.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5, 6.10.12.18.20.</note> to him, <hi>till he comes to known that Ieſus Chriſt (in his</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117964:12"/>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Joh. 3.34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.33. Rom. 12.3. &amp; 1. Cor. 3.1, 2, 3. &amp; 2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.13, 14, 15. &amp; 12.7 Gal. 4.19. Eph. 4.7.13.16. Heb. 5.12, 13, 14. &amp; 1 Pet. 2.2. &amp; 1 Joh. 2.1.12, 13, 14.18.28. &amp; 3.7.9.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5 18.20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note> 
                     <hi>meaſure</hi>) <hi>is that light within every</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 1.9 <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.33.51. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.12. and 9.5. and 12.35.36, 46 Mat. 24.14. Luk. 3.6. Act. 2.37. Rom. 1.19.21, &amp;c. &amp;. 2.14, 15. &amp; 5.8.18. &amp; 1 Cor. 15.22. &amp;. 2 Cor. 5.14, 15. Eph. 1.23. &amp; 4.6.10. Col. 1.20.23. &amp; 3.11. &amp; 1 Tim. 2.4.6. &amp; 4.10. Tit. 2.11, 12. &amp; 2 Pet. 3.9. &amp; 1 Ioh. 2.2. &amp; 4.14. ſee Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 25.3. &amp; 29.3. &amp; 33.28.30. &amp; 37.19. Pſal. 36.9. &amp; 119.127, 155. Prov. 6.23.</note> 
                     <hi>man, or that voice, or witneſs-bearer of God, though dwelling in the dark, priſon-like, or blinde</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 1.5. &amp; 9.5. &amp; 15.2. &amp; 1 Pet. 3.19. and 2 Cor. 4.3.4, 6. Eph. 2.1, 2, 3. and 4.17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8. and 5.8.12. Act. 26.18. Luk. 1.79. and 4.18. and 11.34, 35, 36. Mat. 6 22, 23. and 13.31, 32</note> 
                     <hi>hearts; that</hi> ſheweth, <hi>checketh,</hi> reproveth, <hi>and convinceth</hi> man of his<note n="l" place="margin">Joh. 16.8, 9, 10, 11. Rom. 1.19. and 2.14, 15. Gen. 4 7.10.13, 14.</note> evil, though never ſo ſecretly<note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 10.5. Eph. 6.17. Heb. 4.12.13. and 1 Joh. 3.20. Rev. 19.15. Jer. 23.29. Pſal. 139.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. Hoſ. 6.5.</note> committed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Chriſt being, wherever he is come in the fleſh of</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">2 Joh. 7. and 1 Joh. 4.23.</note> 
                     <hi>man,</hi> (or raiſed up in the heart of man, to a living and ruling life and<note n="o" place="margin">Joh. 6.54.56. and 15.5 and 13.3.23. Rom 8.2.4.9, 10, 11. and 1 Cot. 6.11.19, 20. and 2 Cor. 3.3, 16.17, 18. and 4.10, 11. Gal 2.20. and 4.5, 6. and 5.5, 16, 1, 8 25. Eph. 2.18, 19, 21, 22. Phil. 3.3. Col. 1.17, 27. and 2.10. and 2 Tim. 4.7. Heb. 10.19, 20. and 12.22, 23, and 1 Pet. 1.3.14, 15, 16, 22, 23. and 2.9. and 3.18. and 4 6 and 1 Joh. 2.20, 27. and 3.9.24. and 4.13.17. and 5.6, 10.18, 20.</note> power) <hi>the ſum, ſubſtance, ſulfilling, end, and perfection of the Law and the Prophets, and all</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 10.4. Col. 2.17, 23. Heb. 7.19, 25, 27. and 8.5. and 9.26 28. and 10. 1 Joh. 4.21.23. Act. 7.48, 49 and 21.28.</note> 
                     <hi>their Adminiſtrations; yea even of</hi> John the Baptiſts <hi>outward, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, Rudimentall water-baptiſm, as well as all the</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 6.3, 4. and 1 Cor. 12, 13. Gal. 3.27. Eph. 4, 5, 6. Col. 2.10, 11, 12. and 1 Pet. 3.21. ſee Joh. 1.32, 33. Matt. 3.11. Mark 1.8. Luk. 3.15, 16. Act. 1.4, 5.8. and 2.4. and 13.24, 25, 49. and 16.4. compared with 1 Cor. 1.14.16, 17. and 7.19. Act. 20.26, 27. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8.30, 31. Rom. 2.28, 29. Gal. 3.28. and 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.9, 10, 11. &amp; 5.16. Eph. 2.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Col. 3.10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>reſt:</hi> Which Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-baptiſm was adminiſtred in Chriſt and his Apoſtles time (ſo long as it laſted) <hi>alwayes by thoſe that had their immediate call in spirit, to be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and who in their adminiſtration of their Office, were wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers up and down, without a certain dwelling, or outward abiding</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Luk 1.4, 5.11.13.15, 16 17.41.44.66. &amp; 3.2 &amp; 20.4, 5, 6. Mat. 31.3.13.15. &amp; 21.25, 26. Mar. 11.30, 31, 32. Act. 1.5.8. and 2.4.38. (and 6.3, compared with ch. 8.5.12, 13.16.26, 27.36, 37, 38, 39.) and 9.6.11.17, 18. and 10.44.47, 48. and 13.1, 2, 4. and 16.3.4.6.9, 10.14, 15.31.33. and 19. i, 2, 3, 4. and 1 Cor. 4.9. 1. Gal. 1.1.12.15, 16. Ep. 1.17. and 3.3.</note> 
                     <hi>place.</hi> Which ſoid Light of Chriſt, teacheth and directs man, and leads him<note n="s" place="margin">Prov. 6.22.23. Eſa. 2.3. &amp; 30.7.15.20, 21. &amp; 44.2, 3. &amp; 51.7. &amp; 54.13. Ier: 24.7. &amp; 31.34. Ezek. 27.22. to 28. &amp; 34.21. to 26. &amp; 36.24, 25. Ioel 2.28, 29. Ioh. 6.45, 46. &amp; 10.7.9.16. &amp; 14.6.16, 17.26. and 15.5.15. and 16.13.25. Act. 2.16, 17, 18. Rom. 10.7, 8, 9. Heb. 8.8, 9, 10, 11. and 10.16.20. and 1 Ioh. 2.20.27. and 5.20. Rev. 7.17. and 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.6, 22, 23.</note> up (if heed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and guided by it, and ſubmiſſively, patiently, and<note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 7.17. and 8.12.47. and 11.9, 10. and 15.2.4, 5, 6, 7.10.14. Col. 1.22, 23. Heb. 5.8, 9. and 3.14. Act. 5.3.</note> perſeveringly obeyed) into that living life and<note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12. and 6.33.35.40.51.54, 55, 56, 57, and 7.37.39. and 11.25, 26.</note> power, where purity
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117964:12"/>and holineſs, is<note n="w" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1, 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.18, 19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6, 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.15.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.5.7, 9.11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21, 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.23, 24. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.10, 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.13.</note> ſeen, and perfect cleanſing, or <hi>waſhing</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6, 7, 17, 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.15 <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24, 25. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26, 27. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.7.10, 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22, 23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.14.</note> 
                     <hi>from the filth, or act of fin, as well as from its guilt or puniſhment, as injoyed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally poſſeſſed;</hi> yet, even where the very preſence and face<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.22, 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.21, 22, 23, 24, 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.12, 13, 14. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.7.10, 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.17.</note> of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſeen and really injoyed, or <hi>where Righteouſneſs, perfect peace, and compleat joy</hi> (without ſorrow) in the<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.23, 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.16, 17, 20, 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.17, 21, 22, 23, 24.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.13, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5, 21. <hi>Eph</hi> 5.5, 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> i <hi>Theſ.</hi> i. i. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> i. i. <hi>&amp;</hi> i <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.14, 5, 16 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.3, 4, 11, 22, 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22, i, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> Holy Ghoſt, in the heart is clearly poſſeſſed.</p>
                  <p>The rejection, deſpiſing, and contemning of this Light, (the true, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and only infallible<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.20, 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35.8. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.7, 8, 13, 15, 25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.16, 20. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.20.27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.17.</note> guide of every true Chriſtian) is condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the Lord, to all and euery one of thoſe that ſo<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.19, 20, 36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.38, 48. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.21, 24, 47, 51. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.25. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.37. <hi>ſer Iob.</hi> 24.13, 16.</note> contemn, and deſpiſeth this onely, alone, and true guide, the light of Chriſt in the ſoul.</p>
                  <p>This I ſend unto thee at the preſent, thus in print, without ſending it in writing to thee at all; becauſe although much diſturbance, or outſide trouble of late I have had by the <hi>blaſphemous Scriblings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſent unto me, by, and of thy brother, <hi>Ieremiah Elſreath,</hi> who after he had ſent me in writing his 31. confuſed and ignorant quaeries, <hi>&amp;c. in his after-daring, and greatly provoking Letter, the</hi> 19th. <hi>of the firſt moneth laſt by-paſt, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires my Anſwer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in writing to them, boaſtingly ſaying,</hi> to me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall anſwer you all, and upon deſire, procure the approbation of a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient number of hands, to make the (his ſaid) Anſwer a generall act: And although he had a particular Reply to his Anſwer to deceaſed [in <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Goal] <hi>Iames Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nels</hi> fourty three quaeries to the Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts of Fenſtanton in Cambridge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> recorded in that excellent and very much uſefull Book of his, called the <hi>VVATCHER,</hi> pag. 32, 33, 34. and a particular Anſwer to his own thirty one quaeries, and that from an able and ſavoury ſoul, commonly called <hi>Richard Hubberthorne,</hi> which I did write out fair in my own hand, and ſent it to your Congregation by my faithfull Friend, <hi>Luke Howard,</hi> where, with much ado (long ſince I have underſtood it from him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) he got it publikely read; but yet, for any thing I can hear, thy brother, <hi>Ieremiah Elſreth,</hi> keeps it private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cloſely in his pocket, and dare not be a man of his word to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it, or Reply upon it; but is, as I hear, going to ſea, as formerly he hath done, to take the wages of unrighteouſneſs again, for preaching out of his old bottle, the lying frothy inventions of his own corrupt, and meer carnall heart, to a company of Sea men aboard a Man of War: and therefore ſeeing he is likely to perſevere in not performing his ſaid ſolemn Promiſe, given under his own hand; and ſeeing thou thy ſelf to <hi>Luke Howard,</hi> as he hath often told me, declaredſt by thy own mouth to him; thy avowing <hi>Jeremiah Elſreths</hi> foreſaid thirty one quaeries, in the laſt of which he calls the Doctrines of declaring God within, and Chriſt within, and Spirit within, and Baptiſm within, and Law within, &amp;c. to be monſtrous and Satanicall Doctrines: And ſeeing thou perſevereſt upon all opportunies, with a ſpirit of gall and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, to reproach, perſecute, and blaſpheme the truth of God, as it is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117964:13"/>in Jeſus, truly profeſſed by thoſe ſavoury ſouls that thou calleſt <hi>quakers:</hi> I am therefore by the meaſure of God dwelling in my ſoul, at this time thus compelled, and thus enabled to write to thee, requiring thy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to theſe my lines to thee, that ſo as God ſhall come in with renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of ſtrength and ability into my ſoul, according to his<note n="e" place="margin">Eſa. 40.28, 29, 30, 31.</note> recorded promiſe, I may in the face of the Son endeavour before the ſons and daughters of God, for to manifeſt my faith to be founded upon the ſure Rock of Ages, the Lord Jeſus, by replying upon thee, and ſo ſtop thy, and thy ſaid brothers <hi>blaſphemous mouths</hi> againſt the pure truth of God: And therefore as a witneſs bearer to this I ſubſcribe my name as known unto thee to be only,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> 
                        <date>this 25. of the third month, 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Iohn Lilburns.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
